<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>open-source on Sayak Dattagupta</title>
    <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/tags/open-source/</link>
    <description>Recent content in open-source on Sayak Dattagupta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/tags/open-source/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Use copyleft licensing</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/21/use-copyleft-licensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/21/use-copyleft-licensing/</guid>
      <description>There is no correlation between open-source code and open relationships. But people unwise enough to use a certain kind of license can be metaphorically forced into a variation of the latter. Shocking? Keep reading to learn more.
GPLv3 (and its SaaS equivalent, AGPLv3) is a &amp;lsquo;copyleft&amp;rsquo; license. Whenever any entity (individual or corporate) utilizes GPLv3 (or its prior iterations) licensed code in their own software, they are forced to share the codebase of the said piece of software in a similarly &amp;lsquo;free&amp;rsquo; or open-source manner — thereby maintaining &amp;lsquo;reciprocity&amp;rsquo; and ensuring that originally open-source code doesn&amp;rsquo;t get absorbed into some proprietary codebase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LibrExam (the birth of)</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/17/librexam-the-birth-of/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/17/librexam-the-birth-of/</guid>
      <description>Mock tests are a global phenomenon. Every student — from American AP Physics 2 bros to Chinese Gaokao tryhards to Indian JEE Advanced sweats — takes them. And they usually cost a pretty penny.
Breaking Bad the mock examinations cartel. Not anymore.
Goodbye legacy, propeitary, limited-in-scope-and-content test taking software. Welcome LibrExam. Welcome its AGPL-3 License (I am looking at you, Microsoft*).
The fundamental idea behind LibrExam is that it&amp;rsquo;s kind of decentralised.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shun YouTube on Android, use NewPipe</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/05/08/shun-youtube-on-android-use-newpipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/05/08/shun-youtube-on-android-use-newpipe/</guid>
      <description>NewPipe is a libre (Free, with a capitalized &amp;lsquo;F&amp;rsquo;) frontend for YouTube which runs on Android devices.
The inconvenience, data collection, and speed issues of YouTube had bothered me for quite a while before I finally decided to switch to an open-source, preferably Free, alternative. It does have a trending tab, though, and the last time I checked, it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be turned off. However, this isn&amp;rsquo;t a huge issue since recurring MrBeast content isn&amp;rsquo;t very tempting anyway.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
