<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Sayak Dattagupta</title>
    <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Sayak Dattagupta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Use copyleft licensing</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/21/use-copyleft-licensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/21/use-copyleft-licensing/</guid>
      <description>There is no correlation between open-source code and open relationships. But people unwise enough to use a certain kind of license can be metaphorically forced into a variation of the latter. Shocking? Keep reading to learn more.
GPLv3 (and its SaaS equivalent, AGPLv3) is a &amp;lsquo;copyleft&amp;rsquo; license. Whenever any entity (individual or corporate) utilizes GPLv3 (or its prior iterations) licensed code in their own software, they are forced to share the codebase of the said piece of software in a similarly &amp;lsquo;free&amp;rsquo; or open-source manner — thereby maintaining &amp;lsquo;reciprocity&amp;rsquo; and ensuring that originally open-source code doesn&amp;rsquo;t get absorbed into some proprietary codebase.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LibrExam (the birth of)</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/17/librexam-the-birth-of/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/07/17/librexam-the-birth-of/</guid>
      <description>Mock tests are a global phenomenon. Every student — from American AP Physics 2 bros to Chinese Gaokao tryhards to Indian JEE Advanced sweats — takes them. And they usually cost a pretty penny.
Breaking Bad the mock examinations cartel. Not anymore.
Goodbye legacy, propeitary, limited-in-scope-and-content test taking software. Welcome LibrExam. Welcome its AGPL-3 License (I am looking at you, Microsoft*).
The fundamental idea behind LibrExam is that it&amp;rsquo;s kind of decentralised.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Subscribe to some RSS Feeds</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/05/11/subscribe-to-some-rss-feeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/05/11/subscribe-to-some-rss-feeds/</guid>
      <description>RSS (&amp;lsquo;Really Simple Syndication&amp;rsquo;) feeds are an excellent way to stay up-to-date with recent posts on a website that supports them. Basically, think of it as a newsletter or notifier, but without the bloat, and with the added advantage of (usually) being able to read the said article in it&amp;rsquo;s entirety. To get started with &amp;ldquo;subscribing&amp;rdquo; to RSS feeds, you simply need a RSS reader. I recommend Feeder (I would prefer you use F-Droid, or Droidify, to install it, instead of the Play Store) on Android.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shun YouTube on Android, use NewPipe</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/05/08/shun-youtube-on-android-use-newpipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/post/2025/05/08/shun-youtube-on-android-use-newpipe/</guid>
      <description>NewPipe is a libre (Free, with a capitalized &amp;lsquo;F&amp;rsquo;) frontend for YouTube which runs on Android devices.
The inconvenience, data collection, and speed issues of YouTube had bothered me for quite a while before I finally decided to switch to an open-source, preferably Free, alternative.
With NewPipe you can:
Avoid Ads. Save videos as actual redistributable files, like a .mp4. Play videos on the background. Avoid recommendations that are &amp;ldquo;tailor-made&amp;rdquo; by analyzing your watch history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>I like writing useful programs, peddling FOSS, anything mechanical, working-out, making music, consooming movies, and being opinionated.
Me, 2025 This site is made in Hugo, using the theme hugo-xmin. It has further been tastefully modified by me – it now has a dark color theme, a different article layout, and it incorporates responsiveness, a reading list, and a movie-watching list that loads from a JSON (I have not included the Python script that generates it in my source).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Movies and TV Shows</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/movies/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/movies/</guid>
      <description>Here are some movies and TV shows that I have watched.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Reading List</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/reading/</guid>
      <description>Here are some books that I am reading/have read. This list is incomplete, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have plenty of books that I have read, but I will keep updating it whenever I want to.
2024 Published: 2016
&#34;A candid and riveting memoir by Nike co‑founder Phil Knight, recounting the company’s scrappy origins and relentless ambition.&#34;
My Thoughts: An excellent biography. Published: 1922
&#34;H. G. Wells distills the story of humanity into an accessible journey from prehistory to the modern age.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Skills</title>
      <link>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sayakdattagupta.github.io/skills/</guid>
      <description>Here are some things that I know.
Programming Languages C (SDL2) C++ (SFML, SDL2) C# (for Unity) JavaScript (pure, vue) Java (only upto the level taught at high school) Python (matplotlib, numpy, scipy, selenium, geckodriver, flask, Tkinter) Bash HTML and CSS (no frameworks) Tools &amp; Systems I practically only use a desktop Linux setup (Debian/Arch + i3/dwm) these days and can get along with it just fine, but I will refrain from calling Linux to be a &amp;ldquo;skill&amp;rdquo; of mine since I have no proper knowledge about things like kernel programming, yet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
